基於真實故事
1953年肯尼亞在基庫尤人組成的茅茅黨帶領下
爆發了反對英國殖民統治的武裝起義
在這場鬥爭中  數千人喪生
超過一百萬基庫尤人被送入拘留營
鬥爭終於贏來了獨立
但是對很多人來說  過去難以釋懷
片名:  「一年級生」
同胞們，同胞們
My People, my people.
現在，新政府宣佈
Now, the new government has announced
全民享受免費教育
free education for all.
他們只要你出現帶著出生證明來
All they want is for you to turn up with a birth certificate.
一個會信守諾言的政府?  難以置信!
A government that keeps its promise? Unbelievable!
我兒子需要接受教育
My son needs to be educated.
他叫卡莫.切赫，卡莫.切赫 切赫！
Kamau Chege, Kamau Chege. Chege!
珍妮老師  珍妮老師!  過來  他要見你
Teacher Jane, Teacher Jane! Come on, he's asking for you.
請過來一下! Please!
凱瑟琳老師!
Teacher Katherine!
凱瑟琳老師  你能來一下嗎?
Teacher Katherine, can you come?
好的  請給我一點時間
OK, give me a moment, please.
這張不是出生證  老媽媽  你不是最先到的
This is not a birth certificate. Mama, you are not the first.
有什麼可以幫到你的? 老人家
May' help you, mzee?
這裡是一所小學
This is a primary school.
"新政府承諾全民可免費接受初等教育"
"The new government promises free primary education for all"
老人家，他們指的是孩子，不是成年人
Mzee, they meant children, not adults.
不  我親耳從收音機裡聽到的
No. I heard on the radio, with my own ears.
他們說每個人都可以
They said everybody.
我們有200個學生卻只有50張桌子  看看這個
We have 200 students and only 50 desks. Look at this.
我們不能把它們浪費在一個一隻腳進墳墓的老人身上
We can't waste them on an old man with one foot in the grave.
老人家，你的練習本在哪裡？
Mzee, where are your exercise books?
你要有兩個練習本  以及一支鋒利的HB鉛筆
You need two, and one HB pencil, sharp,
一頭帶橡皮擦
with a rubber on one end.
這些是入學規定
Those are the regulations.
不，老人家，不
Pole, mzee. Pole.
馬魯格  馬魯格
Maruge maruge
一起來喝酒吧!  人生苦短  啤酒甘美
Let's have a drink! Life is short beer is sweet
馬魯格才不屑跟我們一起喝酒呢!
Maruge doesn't care to drink with us!
早上好  孩子們
Good morning, boys and girls.
早上好，女士！
Good morning, madam!
你們好嗎? 很好，謝謝你，女士！
How are you? Fine, thank you, madam!
你們好嗎?  你好嗎? 夫人
How do you do? How do you do, madam?
我很好，謝謝你們
I do very well, thank you.
我很高興你們都來到我的教室上課
I am so excited to have you here all in my classroom.
歡迎 卡里布尼  請坐下
Welcome. Karibuni. Sit down, please.
謝謝你，女士
Thank you, madam.
現在，我知道你們有些人可能有點緊張
Now, I know that some of you may be a little nervous,
但是沒什麼好害怕的
but there's nothing to be afraid of.
學習就是要有樂趣，所以我們都是來這裡找樂趣的
Learning is about having fun, so we are all here to have fun.
不是嗎? 是的
Si ndiyo? Yes.
好的，讓我查一下 每個人都有自己的書嗎？
Alright, let me check. Has everybody got their books?
是的! 非常好!
Yes! Very good!
而且每個人都有鉛筆嗎？有!
And has everybody got their pencils? Yes!
好啊! 好的...我聽到有人說沒有  誰說沒有的?
OK. Good...I heard a few noes. Who said no?
好吧，噢! 佛蘭西斯，你能來發一下鉛筆嗎? 拜託
OK, well, Francis, can you give out some pencils, please?
好了...OK...
帕里斯和波林  請到前面來
Paris and Pauline, come to the front, please.
所以 大家記得明天要帶你的課本和你的鉛筆來
So, everyone, tomorrow, your books and your pencils.
是的 好的 非常好  非常好
Yes. OK, very good, very good.
抱歉，抱歉，對不起
Sorry, sorry, excuse me.
回家去吧!  老人家  我看得出來你生活很艱難
Go home, mzee. I can see you've had a hard life.
回家好好休息吧!
Go home and rest in peace.
好好休息?
Rest in peace?
我還沒死 I'm not dead.
聽著 老人家...
Look, mzee...
我叫奇曼尼·囊·馬魯格
My name is Kimani Ng'ang'a Maruge.
噢! 奇曼尼·囊·馬魯格
Well, Kimani Ng'ang'a Maruge,
我們不能接收沒穿校服的人
we cannot accept anyone without a school uniform,
而且這也意味著要穿校鞋
and that means school shoes too.
而且你沒錢買這些東西
And you do not have money for such things.
珍妮? Jane?
老人家，為什麼你那麼老了還想上學
Mzee, why does someone as old as you want to go to school?
我想學習閱讀
I want to learn to read.
我們的學生已經太多了
We've got too many pupils already.
我希望我能幫助你
I wish I could help you.
我很抱歉 不
I'm sorry. Pole.
"總統辦公室"
"Office of the president"
好的 我們到了
Alright, here we are.
好吧，非常感謝  謝謝
OK, asante sana. Asante.
再見  老師
Goodbye, Teacher.
你記得我跟你說過的那個老頭嗎？
You know that old man I told you about?
他又回來了
He came back again.
我希望你沒有讓他入學
I hope you did not let him in.
這個可憐的老男孩可能老了
The poor old boy might be senile.
你為什麼不堅持你能贏的戰役，嗯？
Why don't you stick to battles you can win, hm?
比如找更多的桌子
Like finding more desks.
你這周過得怎樣?
How was your week?
瑞典公司沒付我咨詢費
The Swedish company hasn't paid me the consulting fee.
政府的工作開始聽起來很有吸引力
The government job is starting to sound very appealing.
除了必須待在奈洛比做全職這一點
Except it had to be full time in Nairobi,
然後我們就再也見不到對方了
and then we'd never see each other at all.
如果你也來奈洛比的話就不會了
Not if you came to Nairobi.
我們將住在一所大房子裡，生孩子
We'll live in a big house, make babies.
生一群小歐賓舒
Have a little bunch of Obinchus.
查爾斯，我不能
Charles, I can't.
學校需要我
The school needs me.
那我呢?
What about me?
你把我難倒了
You've got me.
你好女士  我要買些衣服
Hello, ma'am I need to buy some clothes
你穿這件好看
It looks good on you
這件多少錢
How much is this one
我算你便宜點
I'll make it cheaper for you
幫我放到一邊
Put this aside for me
你日子過得真滋潤呀!
You are living a good life!
帶著三個老婆買東西
Shopping with three wives
我們這裡五個孩子共用一張桌子 先生
We've got five children to a desk here, sir.
還有孩子坐地板上
There are children sitting on the floor.
他們不能這樣學習，奇普托先生
They can't work like this, Mr Kipruto.
你需要為每一個新生的孩子準備一份表格，一式三份？
You need a form for every single new child, in triplicate?
不，你不是認真的 我沒時間這麼做，奇普托先生
No, you can't be serious. I don't have time to do that, Mr Kipruto.
你能不能僅僅相信我的話?
Could you not just take my word for it?
是的，我知道，要按規定
Yes, I know, regulations.
我也祝你日安，奇普托先生
Good day to you too, Mr Kipruto.
我該怎麼辦? 阿爾佛雷德
What am I to do, Alfred?
我們尊敬的首長已做出了一項行政決定
Our esteemed superintendent has made one of his executive decisions.
你一定要來看看這個
You've got to see this.
什麼? What?
你不會輕易放棄的，對吧? 馬魯格
You don't give up easily, do you, Maruge?
你不能上當
You can't fall for this.
當局會找你麻煩的
You'll be asking for trouble with the authorities.
你知道他是對的，馬魯格？
You know he's right, Maruge?
我怎麼向教育委員會交代?
What will I say to the board of education?
嗯? Hm?
我該怎麼跟孩子們的父母交代?
What will I say to the parents?
我會當個好學生
I'll be a good pupil.
我會努力學習
I'll work very hard.
如果奇浦路托發現...
If Kipruto finds out...
奇浦路托不是這裡的頭兒，阿爾弗雷德
Kipruto's not the head here, Alfred.
而是我 I am.
讓他入學 Let him in.
我正在做一個行政決策
I'm making an executive decision.
批准馬魯格入學
Let Maruge in.
馬魯格? 歡迎
Maruge? Welcome.
歡迎 Karibu.
謝謝 Thank you.
佛蘭西斯，回座位坐好
Francis, take your seat.
同學們，今天我們來了個新同學
Class, we have a new student today,
而他德名字叫馬魯格
and his name is Maruge.
歡迎，馬魯格!
Welcome, Maruge!
我來這裡跟你們一起學習
珍妮弗，請舉一下妳的手
Jennifer, raise your hand, please.
想讓你坐在珍妮弗旁邊
I would like you to go and sit next to Jennifer
就在後面那裡，請，馬魯格
at the back there, please, Maruge.
如果我坐得太遠，我就看不見了 我不能
If I sit far, I can't see. I can't.
好吧! OK.
嗯...蘇珊，你能坐在那裡嗎？
Uh...Suzanne, can you sit there?
莎拉，你能坐尼維旁邊嗎？拜託
Sarah, can you sit next to Niva, please?
馬魯格，你可以坐在那裡
Maruge, you can sit there.
坐在尼維旁邊，好嗎？莎拉
Sit next to Niva, OK, Sarah?
往後坐一點  好嗎? 很好
Back down. Yes? Good.
我們開始上課!
Let's begin!
打開練習本
Open your exercise books.
鉛筆好又尖
Pencils nice and sharp.
好又尖!
Nice and sharp!
我的鉛筆是我的朋友
My pencil is my friend.
我把它一直握在手
I keep him to the end.
我的鉛筆是我的朋友
My pencil is my friend.
我把它一直握在手
I keep him to the end.
好的 今天我們從小寫字母開始學
OK, we are going to begin with small letters today,
以字母“a”開始，好嗎？
beginning with the letter 'A', OK?
這就是我們寫小寫字母“a”的方式
And this is how we write our small letter 'A'.
好吧，先是胖胖的，然後瘦瘦的
OK, a fatty, a thinny.
胖胖的，瘦瘦的
A fatty, a thinny.
請繼續寫你的小寫字母"a"
Please continue writing your lower-case 'A's.
布蘭登，布蘭登 對不起，親愛的
Brendan, Brendan. Sorry, darling.
馬魯格，鉛筆是這樣握的
Maruge, this is how you hold a pencil.
好的，你把它夾在你的拇指和食指之間
OK, you hold it between your thumb and your first finger.
非常好  然後你輕輕地按，不要太用力，好嗎？
Very good. And you press lightly not too hard, OK?
非常好 Very good.
好，我們繼續，跟著我重複練習
Good, we are continuing, repeating after me.
先是胖胖的
A fatty,
然後瘦瘦的
a thinny.
胖胖的 A fatty,
瘦瘦的 a thinny.
胖胖的，瘦瘦的...
A fatty, a thinny...
"奇曼尼·囊·馬魯格: 84分"
卡卯，過來
Kamau, come here.
那個穿校服的老頭是怎麼回事?
What's with the old man in uniform?
是的，他在我們學校上學
Yeah, he's in our school.
進去並開始寫功課
Get inside and start working.
快點 Come on.
別吵  你們這些醉鬼  我要去上學
Don't make any noise, you drunkards. I'm going to school
過來 Come here
小男生上哪去呀!
Where are the boy going!
老頭  你會惹麻煩的
Old man, you'll get into trouble
F-I-T
F-I-T.
瘦瘦的 A thinny.
F-I-T
F-I-T.
"Fit(合適)" 'Fit'.
F-I-T
F-I-T.
瘦瘦的 A thinny.
馬魯格! Maruge!
離學校遠點，蛤？
Stay out of the school, huh?
學校不是老頭去的地方!
School is no place for an old man!
你不屬於那裡!
You don't belong there!
起來  起來 Get up. Get up.
站成一排! Get into line!
走開! 別擋路!
Move! Get out of the way!
出來! Move out!
他們在哪裡，茅茅黨?
Where are they, the Mau Mau?
寫得很好，彼得
Well done, Peter.
掌聲鼓勵彼得!
Makofi for Peter!
幹得好，幹得好，彼得
Well done, well done, Peter.
再接再厲  好孩子!
Try again another day. A wonderfulboy!
好的，誰來給我寫一下數字"4"?
OK, who's going to write for me the number four?
數字"4"? 誰來給我寫一下?
The number four? Who is going to write for me?
蘇珊娜 蘇珊娜，過來 來給我寫數字4
Suzanne. Suzanne, come. Come and write for me the number four.
很好，蘇珊娜
Well done, Suzanne.
請掌聲鼓勵蘇珊娜
Makofi for Suzanne, please.
幹得好，幹得好，蘇珊娜！
Well done, well done, Suzanne!
再接再厲  一個很棒的女孩！
Try again another day. A wonderfulgirl!
一個很棒的女孩！非常好!
A wonderful girl! Very good.
好的，4接下來就是5
OK, next after four is five.
誰來給我寫一下數字"5"?
Who is going to write the number five for me?
卡卯，來給我們寫一下數字"5"字
Kamau, come and write the number five for us.
來 Come.
來寫一下數字"5"
Come and write the number five
這樣我們都知道如何寫數字"5"
so that we all know how to write the number five.
別笑了! Stop it!
我們是這樣寫數字"5"的嗎?
Is that how we write the number five?
不是 No.
不，不是這樣寫的，卡卯
No, it is not, Kamau.
我是開玩笑的
I was just kidding.
好的 不許再開玩笑了
OK. No more jokes.
非常好!  非常好，卡卯
Excellent! Very good, Kamau.
請掌聲鼓勵卡卯
Makofi for Kamau, please.
幹得好，幹得好，卡卯
Well done, well done, Kamau.
再接再厲  好孩子
Try again another day. A wonderful boy.
好的，馬魯格，你來給我們寫一下數字"6"好嗎?
OK, Maruge, can you come and write for us the number six?
馬魯格!  你來給我們寫一下數字"6"好嗎?
Maruge! Can you come and write the number six for us?
馬魯格! Maruge!
嘿! 別寫了 Hey, stop.
馬魯格，你來給我們寫一下數字"6"好嗎?
Maruge, will you write the number six for us?
好的，還有誰可以給我寫數字"6"?
OK, can someone else write me the number six?
誰給我寫一下數字"6"?
Who is going to write me the number six?
你病了嗎? Are you sick?
我沒病 I'm not sick
我耳朵不好使
My ears don't work wel
就這樣 That's it
等我長大了
When I grow up
我要當醫生治好你
I want to be a doctor to cure you
同學們 早上好
Good morning, class.
早上好，阿爾佛雷德老師
Good morning, Teacher Alfred.
阿爾佛雷德老師要來檢查一下書寫是否整潔，好嗎？
Teacher Alfred is going to inspect for neatness, yes?
好了，坐下，坐下
OK, sit down, sit down.
謝謝你 老師
Thank you, Teacher.
帕切科，嗯-嗯! 好，好，好
Patrick, hm-hm. Good, good, good.
波林，好
Pauline. Good.
很好 Good.
日期在哪裡?
Where is the date?
好，好，好
Good, good, good.
馬魯格，你的鉛筆變鈍了
Maruge, your pencil's very blunt.
你在樹立什麼樣的榜樣？
What kind of example are you setting?
現在快去削尖，以後別再這樣了
Go sharpen it now and don't let it happen again.
瑪麗莎，瑪麗莎，瑪麗莎
Malisa, Malisa, Malisa.
要我幫你好讓你聽得清楚點嗎?
Should I help you to hear a little bit better?
像這樣，馬魯格
Like this, Maruge.
馬魯格? 我們出去透透氣吧!
Maruge? Let's get you some air.
他怎麼了?  你先看著學生
What's wrong with him? Stay with my class.
不是我的錯!
It wasn't me!
怎麼了? 馬魯格
What's wrong, Maruge?
我想學習對年紀大的你來說太吃力了，馬魯格
I think this is all too much for you at your age, Maruge.
也許你不該來上學
Maybe you shouldn't be here.
這不會再發生了
It won't happen again.
那個是什麼?
What is that?
我進過拘留營
I was in the camps.
你是茅茅黨員?
You were Mau Mau?
是的 Yes.
告訴我剛才在教室到底是怎麼回事，馬魯格
Tell me what happened in the classroom, Maruge.
然後我可以幫你
Then I can help you.
我必須回教室去上課完成我的作業了
I must go back to class to finish my work.
我鄭重起誓:
I solemnly swear:
我會為我們的土地和自由抗爭
I will fight for our land and freedom
再也不受白人凌辱
No more Insulted by white people
再也不會讓他們奪走我們的土地  屠殺我們的家人
Never let them take our land and kill our families again
如果我違背誓言
If I break my oath
就讓這誓言殺死我
Let this oath kill me
這是什麼?
What is this?
我曾經是個囚犯
I was a prisoner.
為什麼? 你做錯事了嗎?
Why? did you do something wrong?
是白人
It's white people
他們偷走了我們的土地
The stole our land,
所以我們說他們必須把它歸還給我們
so we said they must give it back.
他們告訴我們要安靜
They told us to be quiet.
所以我們大聲說出來
So we spoke very loud.
那他們還了嗎?
Did they gave it back?
對一些人來說
To some,
1963年(肯尼亞宣佈獨立)
1963 (Kenya declares independence)
in 1963.
那就是烏乎魯
That was uhuru.
"烏乎魯"是什麼意思?
What does 'uhuru' mean?
就是"自由"
It's 'freedom'.
自由! Freedom!
自由! 自由!
Freedom! Freedom!
烏乎魯! 烏乎魯!
Uhuru! Uhuru!
自由! 自由!
Freedom! Freedom!
烏乎魯! 烏乎魯!
Uhuru! Uhuru!
自由! 自由!
Freedom! Freedom!
烏乎魯! 烏乎魯!
Uhuru! Uhuru!
自由! 自由!
Freedom! Freedom!
烏乎魯! 烏乎魯!
Uhuru! Uhuru!
這是怎麼回事?
What is this?
他會給我們所有人帶來麻煩的
He's going to be a problem, for all of us.
來吧! 到外面來，並開始工作
Come on! Come outside and start working.
我跟你說
Let me tell you something
米歇爾·奧巴馬(美國第一夫人)
Michelle Obama (first lady of the United States)
是南非人
is South African
不對  她是肯尼亞人
No, she's Kenyan
她曾經跟我女兒一起上學
She went to school with my daughter
你們什麼都不知道
You guys know nothing
他跟那些小孩一塊上學很不妥當
It's not proper for him to go to school with those children
聽著，朋友
Listen, my friend.
不一定要這樣
It doesn't have to be like this.
放棄你的誓言，你就可以回家了
Renounce your oath and you can go home.
放棄你的誓言!
Renounce the oath!
再來 Again.
同胞們，我的同胞們
People, my people
我聽到有傳聞說
I'm hearing rumblings
一位老人實際上已經回到了學校
that an old man has actually gone back to school.
一個老人回學校了！
An old man going back to school!
難以置信 Unbelievable.
做得很好
Excellent work.
來，卡卯
Come, Kamau.
我們看看你的作業做的怎樣
Let's see what you have done.
你的很好
Your one's very good.
非常好，非常好
Very good, very good.
卡卯，你的"5"又寫錯了
Your fives again, Kamau.
我們沒複習過這個嗎? 我們複習過了的
Did we not go over this? Yes.
那你為什麼又把它們寫錯了呢？
So why have you written them the wrong way again?
嗯? Hm?
卡卯，你必須再寫一遍
You have to write them again, Kamau.
知道了嗎? 知道了 老師
Sawa? Yes, Miss.
馬魯格? Maruge?
非常好 Excellent.
你的數字學得很好，馬魯格
You are good with your numbers, Maruge.
出色的工作
Excellent work.
非常好  我很為你高興
Very good. I'm very happy with you.
來吧，法蘭西斯 讓我們看看你做了什麼
Come, Francis. Let's take a look at what you have done.
哦，我喜歡  你的功課總是很整潔
Oh, I like that. Your work is always very neat.
你是個很聰明的孩子
You're a very clever boy.
好的 非常好
OK. Excellent.
因為你做得很好，你會得到一顆星
Because you have done so well, you're going to get a star.
噢! 你弄疼我了!
Ow! You're hurting me!
馬魯格! Maruge!
你不能打他!
You do not hit him!
老實說，女人告訴我基庫尤人骨子裡有瘋狂的血液
Honestly, ladies tell me Kikuyus have mad blood,
但是他們背後的故事又是另一回事了
but their back story's another one.
基庫尤人像種馬一樣工作 他們非常...
Kikuyus work like stallions. They're very...
馬魯格，住手! 馬魯格!
Maruge, stop it! Maruge!
住手! 嘿!
Stop it! Hey!
嘿，嘿，嘿！這是怎麼回事？
Hey, hey, hey! What's going on here?
當我接到媒體的電話時，我簡直不敢相信自己的耳朵
I couldn't believe my ears when I got a phone call from the press
告訴我在我的一所小學裡有一位老人！
telling me about an old man in one of my primary schools!
他是誰? 為什麼他穿著校服?
Who is he? Why is he in school uniform?
他叫馬魯格
His name is Maruge.
老人家 M Mzee
誰准許你進來的
Who allowed you in
他想上學，所以我就讓他進來了
He wanted to come to school, so I let him.
你什麼意思? 這是一所小學
What do you mean? This is a primary school.
先生，政府說每個人都有上學的權利
Sir, the government said everybody has the right to go to school.
僅僅因為我們的政客愚蠢並不意味著我們也必須愚蠢！
Just because our politicians are stupid doesn't mean we have to be as well!
他不能待在這裡
He can't stay here.
成年人必須去成人學校
Adults must go to the adult school.
現在，確保他現在離開這裡
Now, see to it that he leaves here now.
先生，他與英國人作戰
Sir, he fought the British.
他被囚禁在拘留營裡 哦，原來是茅茅黨的，蛤？
He was imprisoned in the camps. Oh, Mau Mau, huh?
典型基庫尤人  我早該知道的
Typical Kikuyu. I should have known.
你說什麼? Excuse me?
我以為部落主義已經結束了
I thought tribalism was over.
這跟部落主義沒關係
This has nothing to do with tribalism.
這是為了做對學校有利的事
It's about doing what's right for the school.
像他這樣的老人不應該待在滿是孩子的教室裡
An old man like him does not belong in a classroom full of children.
現在，這件事我們到辦公室再繼續說
Now, we'll continue this conversation in the office.
馬魯格...Maruge...
他們是血腥的卡倫金人
He's a bloody Kalenjin.
你不也是嗎? 馬魯格
You too, Maruge?
你知道You were either for them or you were against them,
獨立後，我們都成了肯尼亞人
You know, after independence, we all became Kenyans.
卡倫金人是忠誠的！
The Kalenjins were loyalists!
我的家人也效忠英國人!
So were my family loyal to the British!
想要活命的每個人都是!
So was everybody if they wanted to stay alive!
別那樣看著我  英國人從來沒有給人們一個選擇
And don't look at me like that. The British never gave people a choice.
你要嘛支持他們，或者你要嘛反對他們
You were either for them or you were against them,
而如果你反對他們，他們就殺你
and if you were against them, they killed you.
我有過孩子
I had children.
兩個孩子!
Two children!
我有過一個家!
I had a family!
英國人把他們都殺了
The British killed them.
我們作出了選擇
We chose.
基庫尤人作出了選擇
The Kikuyus chose.
而我們也付出了代價
And we paid.
我們付出了代價!
We paid!
回去上課，回去上課，回去上課，回去上課
Come to class. Come to class, come to class, come to class.
回去上課，回去上課
Go to class, go to class.
他說我必須讓馬魯格退學
He says I've got to get rid of Maruge.
他要送他到成人學校
He's sending him off to the adult school.
他的同情心哪去了?
Where is his compassion?
珍妮，珍妮，別說了
Jane, Jane, just stop.
他不是那麼說的
That's not what he's saying.
他只是說馬魯格不能上小學
He's just saying Maruge cannot go to children's school.
你為什麼要幫他辯護?
Why are you defending him?
英國人殺了他的家人  我們有責任去幫他
The British killed his family. We have a duty to help him.
茅茅黨也殺人，好嗎？
The Mau Mau killed people too, OK?
但是這跟老人上小學的事情無關
But that's got nothing to do with an old man going to a children's school.
好的 Fine.
沒有人會為馬魯格而戰，所以我會的
No-one's going to fight for Maruge, so I will.
好的，請不要越過奇普托的頭
OK, please do not go over Kipruto's head.
我跟這些人一起工作而且我知道他們的情況
I work with these people and I know how they are.
他們對此並不友好
They don't take kindly to this.
你知道我總是站在你這邊的
You know I'm always on your side.
愛你 再見
Love you. 'Bye.
我很感激你的關心，但我無能為力
I appreciate your concern, but my hands are tied.
馬魯格很努力學習
Maruge is such a hard worker.
他是孩子們的好榜樣
He's a great role model for the children.
如果我們讓馬魯格入學，那我們怎麼拒絕其他人?
If we let Maruge in, how can we refuse others?
我們的學校可能會擠滿了老人
Our schools could be flooded with old people.
這將剝奪
This would be taking away
我們為孩子們所需的寶貴資源
from the precious resources we need for our children.
感謝您抽出時間，秘書長女士
Thank you for your time, Madam Secretary.
不客氣 You're welcome.
歐賓舒夫人，有個跟丹麥政府合作的顧問
Mrs Obinchu, one of the consultants working with the Danish Government,
叫查爾斯·歐賓舒
Charles Obinchu.
查爾斯是我丈夫
Charles is my husband.
代我想他問好 我會的
Give him my best. I will.
歐賓舒夫人，孩子是肯尼亞的未來
Mrs Obinchu, the children are Kenya's future.
對不起，馬魯格
I'm sorry, Maruge.
我沒錢，沒錢
I have no money, no money.
天下沒有免費的午餐
There's nothing for free.
你太老了，走不動的
You cannot go, you're too old.
"成人學習中心  力求優秀"
"Adult learning centers strive for excellence"
所以今天我們重點討論單數和複數
So today we're focusing on singular and plural.
讓我們從"床"開始，好嗎？
Let's start with 'bed', alright?
所以，"bed"，bed的複數形式是beds
So, 'bed', the plural for 'bed' is 'beds'.
那就是B-E-D-S
That's B-E-D-S.
好的，所以你只要加一個"S"
Alright, so you just add an 'S'.
好的，現在，"lamp"的複數形式是...
Alright, now, the plural for 'lamp'...
請安靜 Please.
"lamp"的複數形式是...
The plural for 'lamp'...
好的，那"死亡"呢?
Alright, how about 'death'?
"死亡"的複數形式是...
The plural for 'death'...
再見! 謝謝!
Kwa heri! Asante!
待會見，老師
See you later, Teacher.
馬魯格  你在這裡幹什麼?
Maruge, what are you doing here?
進來吧! Come inside.
我發誓要從英國人手裡奪回土地
I took the oath to get our land back from the British.
馬魯格，你不必告訴我這些
Maruge, you don't have to tell me this.
基庫尤人沒有土地意味著什麼?
What is Kikuyu without land?
馬賽人最看重的是牛
The Masai, it's cattle.
但我們最看重的是土地
But for us, it's land.
這就是我們抗爭的原因
That's why we were fighting.
但如果我們不識字，我們什麼都不是
But we are nothing if we cannot read.
我們毫無用處
We are useless.
當我小時候
When I was a boy,
沒有錢用於教育
there was no money for education.
我在一個白人的農場工作
I worked on a white man's farm.
然後就為自由而戰
Then came the fight for freedom.
馬魯格...Maruge...
我有一封信
I have a letter.
你這話是什麼意思?
What do you mean?
這就是我來學校的原因
That's why I came to the school.
我必須親自看
I must read it for myself.
我必須去理解
I have to understand.
求你了 Please.
教我認字，歐賓舒夫人
Teach me to read, Mrs Obinchu.
噢! 我知道我們以前談過很多次關於馬魯格的事
Well, I know we've had this conversation many times before about Maruge,
但我想知道你是否願意重新考慮一下
but I was wondering if you might be willing to reconsider.
奇普托先生，他們只是在成人學校混日子
Mr Kipruto, they just mess around at the adult school.
他什麼也沒學到
He didn't learn a thing.
是的 Yes.
是的，我當然很感激
Yes, of course I'm grateful.
再見 Kwa heri.
馬魯格，對不起  我已經盡力了...
Maruge, I'm very sorry. I've done everything...
那個該死的奇普托可以下地獄！
That bloody Kipruto can go to hell!
成人學校總比沒有強...
The adult school is better than nothing...
我不去! I'm not going!
他是卡倫金人 他的人民與英國人同床共枕
He's Kalenjin. His people were in bed with the British.
該死的忠誠者！
Bloody loyalist!
我不去 不是我！
I'm not going. Not me!
讓他自己上別的學校吧!
Let him go to the other school himself!
A  B  C  D
A, B, C, D
E  F  G  H
E,F,G,H
I  J  K  L
I, J,K, L
M  N  O  P
M, N, O, P
Q  R  S  T...
Q, R, S, T...
U  V  W
U, V, W
X  Y  zeddy  zeddy(小Z  兒語)
X, Y, zeddy, zeddy (little Z children's language)
A  B  C  D
A, B, C, D
E  F  G  H
E,F,G,H
I  J  K  L
I, J, K, L
M  N  O  P
M, N, O, P
Q  R  S  T
Q, R, S, T
U  V  W
U, V, W
X  Y  Z  zeddy
X, Y, Z, zeddy (little Z children's language)
X  Y  Z
X, Y, Z.
現在，同學們，請坐下
Now, class, please sit down.
我是來說再見的
I came to say goodbye.
我告訴他們山羊不識字
I told them a goat cannot read.
山羊不會寫自己的名字
A goat cannot write his name.
他們必須努力學習，否則他們會像我一樣
They must study hard, or they'll be like me
一個不比那隻山羊好多少的老人
an old man no better than that goat.
你知道，山羊是非常聰明的動物
You know, goats are very clever animals.
他們從不放棄
They never give up.
我們可以好好向他們學習
We can learn a very good lesson from them.
同學們，我有重要的事情宣佈
Class, I have an important announcement.
從現在起，馬魯格將成為我的助教
From now on, Maruge is going to be my teaching assistant.
幹得好，幹得好，馬魯格
Well done, well done, Maruge.
我印象深刻
I'm impressed.
你是怎麼讓他們表現得這麼好的？
How did you get them all to behave so well?
我告訴他們，如果他們不規矩，我就用棍子打他們
I told them if they didn't behave, I'll clobber them with my stick.
馬魯格! Maruge!
等等，馬魯格先生來了！
Wait a minute, there's Mr Maruge!
馬魯格先生來了
There's Mr Maruge.
馬魯格先生，馬魯格先生
Mr Maruge, Mr Maruge.
好了，好了! Alright, alright!
拜託，拜託，如果我們接受採訪，至少要有秩序地進行
Please, please, if we're going to do this, let us at least do it in an orderly way.
如果你想和馬魯格說話，一次問一個問題
If you want to speak to Maruge, one question at a time.
他的聽力不好 拜託
His hearing is poor. Please.
馬魯格先生，我是CNN華盛頓的記者
Mr Maruge, CNN Washington.
馬魯格先生，為什麼你年輕的時候不去上學呢?
Mr Maruge, why didn't you go to school when you were younger?
當馬魯格小時候，黑人沒有免費教育
There was no free education for black people when Maruge was a boy.
那現在上學的動機是什麼
What is the motivation now'?
他說什麼?
What did he say?
他說，"筆中自有力量"
He says, the power is in the pen.
讀書是非常重要的
To read is very important.
這是我們脫貧的途徑之一
This is one way of finishing poverty among us.
還有聖經  我不相信教堂的傳教士
And the Bible. I don't trust those preachers in the churches.
誰會？Who does?
馬魯格先生，我是BBC倫敦的記者
Mr Maruge, BBC London.
肯尼亞政府在這個國家的教育方面做得夠多了嗎？
Is the Kenyan Government doing enough for education in this country?
是的，是的，免費教育！對於所有人
Yes, yes, free education! For all.
馬魯格先生，我是NTV奈洛比的記者
Mr Maruge, NTV Nairobi.
你覺得這事對嗎?
Do you think this is right?
她只是在引起人們對她自己和學校的注意
She's just drawing attention to herself and the school.
這對誰都不好
It's not right for anybody.
阿爾佛雷德 Alfred.
嘿? Hey?
你是我認識的最消極的人
You are the most negative person I know.
這對學校來說是件好事 放輕鬆點
This is a good thing for the school. Just relax.
人們，這個世界已經完全瘋了
People, the world has gone absolutely mad.
並且看看，《紐約時報》《洛杉磯時報》《肯尼亞時報》
And look, 'New York Times', 'L.A. Times', 'Kenya Times',
所有的"時報"
all the 'Times',
BBC，《每日電訊報》
BBC, 'Daily Telegraph'.
整個世界都在說，馬魯格，馬魯格!
The world is finally talking, Maruge, Maruge!
還有那個讓84歲的馬魯格入學的老師
And not to forget the teacher who took Maruge to school at 84 years.
全瘋了!
It's absolutely crazy!
現在，這個老人曾經是茅茅黨的退伍軍人，戰士
Now, this mzee was once a Mau Mau veteran, war fighter,
他想讓肯尼亞說...
who wanted Kenya to say...
"能" 'Can'.
現在，儘管他已經上了年紀，但他也在要求免費教育
Now, despite his age, he too is demanding free education
而且校長珍妮·歐賓舒把他迎進了學校
and head teacher Jane Obinchu has welcomed him through the doors.
許多家長感到憤怒
Many parents are outraged
而且覺得這樣一個寶貴的地方不應該浪費在
and feel that such a valuable place should not be wasted
這樣一個老人身上
on such an old man.
而且，隨著情緒越來越高漲
And, as feelings run increasingly high,
毫無疑問，這場爭論將愈演愈烈
this controversy is no doubt set to grow.
哈巴麗·雅可?
Habari yako?
別跟我打招呼
Don't say hello to me
你並不關心我們的孩子  你只關心你自己
You don't care about our children. You only care about yourself.
你想在報紙上露臉
You want your face in the newspapers
這樣你就可以把口袋裝滿錢
so that you can fill your pockets with money.
你竟敢對我這麼說！
How dare you say that to me!
每個孩子對我都很重要，包括你兒子
Every single child is important to me, including your son.
叫哈巴麗·雅可·波羅 對吧? 對
Habari yako, Polo? Mzuri.
請讓開
Please get out of the way
讓開 Get out of the way
這事還沒完呢?
It's not over yet?
茅茅黨  你看到了嗎? 那個標題？
Mau Mau have you seen? The title?
你看到了嗎？你看到標題了嗎？
Have you seen that? Have you seen the title?
84歲  84歲
84 years. 84! 84 years.
返回學校上學
Gone back to school.
你幾歲? 55歲
How old are you? 55.
55歲  你是個蹣跚學步的孩子
55. You are a toddler.
"84歲茅茅黨老兵最終走進學校"
"The 84 year old Mau Mau party veteran finally entered the school"
我可不想我兒子跟一個老頭混在一起！
I don't want my son being mixed with old men!
好的，請大家靜一靜
OK, everybody, please.
我知道你們都很難過
I know that you are all upset.
拜託，你們聽我說好嗎?
Please, would you listen to me?
我認為我們可以從馬魯格身上學到很多東西
I think that we have a lot to learn from Maruge.
他在幫助我們
He's helping us.
好嗎? 孩子們有很多東西可以向老人學習
OK? The children have a lot that they can learn from the old.
我不想讓他教我兒子，蛤？
I don't want him to teach my son, huh?
他算老幾? 他算老幾?
Who is he? Who is he'?
老師在哪裡？
Where is the teachers'?
現在看看這個 肯定不錯
Now look at this. Surely.
你以為你在幹什麼？你在開馬戲團！
What do you think you're doing? You're running a circus!
我叫你擺脫那老頭
I told you to get rid of that old man.
你知道嗎? 奇普托先生
You know what, Mr Kipruto?
你為什麼不坦白說出來？
Why don't you just come clean?
是因為馬魯格老了還是因為他是基庫尤人
Is it because Maruge is old or is it because he's Kikuyu
你不想讓他在這裡？
that you don't want him here?
這與部落無關，歐賓舒夫人!
This is not about tribes, Mrs Obinchu!
你以為你是誰，指揮議程？
Who do you think you are, dictating the agenda?
你只是個員工 你照我說的做
You're an employee. You do as I tell you.
現在，我最後一次警告你 他要去成人學校!
Now, I'm warning you one last time. He goes to the adult school!
他沒有錢，奇普托先生  他不能在其他地方上學
He's got no money, Mr Kipruto. He can't go to school anywhere else.
他很快就有錢了
He will have money soon.
這個基庫尤政府要給茅茅黨人補償金
This Kikuyu government is going to give the Mau Mau compensation money.
補償什麼?  殺了自己的同胞嗎?
Compensation for what? For killing their own people?
奇普托先生...
Mr Kipruto...
我們不能把過去拋在腦後嗎？
can't we just put the past behind us?
過去始終是存在的，歐賓舒夫人
The past is always present, Mrs Obinchu.
永遠不要忘記這一點
Never forget that.
馬魯格 Maruge.
我懷孕了
I'm pregnant
問她，問問她，這是不是她的丈夫?
Ask her. Ask her, is this her husband?
問她，基庫尤人?
Ask her, Kikuyu?
把孩子從她身上抱走
Take the child off her.
把這個孩子從她身上抱走
Take this baby off her.
嘿! 卡卯
Hey, Kamau.
我來教你寫"5"字
Let me teach you to write "5"
老頭你連鉛筆都削不了
Old man, you can't even sharpen a pencil
你怎麼這麼沒禮貌
Why are you so rude
看 看看他的成績
Look. Look at his grades.
他趕不上其他同學
He can't keep up with the others.
你是說我兒子笨嗎?
Meaning that my son is stupid?
我沒說你兒子笨，切格先生
I'm not saying that your son is stupid, Mr Chege.
我想說的是在我們學校
All I'm saying is that in our school
他的學習要達到一定的成就水準
there's a certain level of attainment that he needs to achieve
以便進入下一課
in order to move on to the next class.
否則，他要留級或者去特殊學校
Otherwise, he repeats the same class or goes to special school.
我兒子有權享受免費教育!
My son has a right for free education!
聽清楚了嗎?
Do I make myself clear?
我完全理解，切格先生
I understand perfectly, Mr Chege.
我們盡所能去幫他
We're helping him in every way we can.
你們根本沒幫他! 蛤?
You are not helping him! Huh?
你在忙著和那個愚蠢的老頭子浪費時間
You're busy wasting your time with that stupid old man.
聽著，我在開一家商店，蛤？
Look, I'm running a shop, huh?
而我兒子的數學和科學一定非常好
And my son must be extremely good in mathematics and science.
這是不公平的，而且這是不對的！
This is not fair and this is not right!
切格先生，我...
Mr Chege, I...
你回家後我們會處理的
We'll deal with this when you get home.
噢，我想我們知道他會跳舞 他在教室媢L得怎麼樣？
Well, I guess we know he can dance. How's he getting on in the classroom?
他的數學很好，不過他真正的目的是來識字的
His maths is good, but he really came here to read,
這需要做更多的工作
and it needs a lot more work.
這是關於為每個人找時間
It's about finding time for everyone.
來，來，來 回到課堂上！
Come, come, come. Back to class!
我們去上課吧!
Let's go to class.
好的，馬魯格，讀這個給我聽
OK, Maruge, sound this for me.
S-A-T
把它放在一起...'Sat’
And put it together...'Sat'.
真棒! 非常好
wonderful! Very good.
"蝙蝠" 'Bat'.
幹得好，馬魯格 非常好，非常好
Well done, Maruge. That is very good, very good.
好的，讓我們繼續下一個
OK, let's move on to the next one.
C-A-T
拼一起呢? "Cat(貓)"
Together? 'Cat'.
好極了，馬魯格 非常好
Excellent, Maruge. Very good.
卡卯? Kamau?
我們在這裡上課 請走開
We are working here. Please go away.
課都上完了  請回家吧!
School is over. Please go home.
來  來 Come, come.
"Mat(墊子)"
'Mat'.
哦，馬魯格，你做得太好了
Oh, Maruge, you have done so well.
非常好! Very good!
好的，讓我們複習一下我們的發音
OK, let's go over our sounds
然後我們今天就結束了，好嗎？
and then we'll finish there for today, OK?
"啊"  "巴"  "卡"  "答"...
'Ah', 'buh', 'kuh', 'duh'...
喂? 是珍妮·歐賓舒嗎?
Hello? Jane Obinchu?
是的? Yes?
所以現在你給那老頭單獨授課，是嗎？
So now you are giving private lessons to the old man, eh?
這是誰？Who is this?
我們在監視你
We are watching you.
我們知道那所房子裡只有你一個人
We know you are alone in that house.
你要小心點
You'll want to take care
兄弟! 呼，呼，呼 哇 哇 哇 哇!
Walalaa! Hoo, hoo, hoo. Wa wa wa wa!
現在，這就是所謂的輪子上的錢移動貨幣
Now, that's called money on wheels mobile money.
政客們現在想要什麼？
Politicians what do they want now?
當我長大後，我喜歡開那種車
When I grow up, that's the kind of car I'd like to drive,
但不是作為一個政客
but not as a politician.
歡迎大家
Welcome, everybody
很高興在這裡見到你們
It's good to see you here
歡迎大家
Welcome, everybody
很高興在這裡見到你們
It's good to see you here
歡迎光臨
Welcome here today
歡迎大家
Welcome, everybody
很高興在這裡見到你們...
It's good to see you here...
歡迎  很榮幸你們的光臨
Welcome. We are honoured to have you here.
來自奈洛比的問候 謝謝
Greetings from Nairobi. Asante.
孩子們怎麼樣? 非常好，非常好
How are the kids? Very good, very good.
很高興在這裡見到你們...
It's good to see you here...
這太棒了！你讓我們聲名遠播了，奧賓丘夫人
This is wonderful! You have put us on the map, Mrs Obinchu.
而我們很感謝  謝謝
And we are very grateful. Asante.
沒有水，沒有電，就在一個偏僻的地方
No water, no electricity and right in the middle of nowhere.
大衛，把糖果拿來
David, bring the sweets.
馬魯格先生，很高興見到你
Mr Maruge, nice to meet you.
很高興見到你 謝謝
Nice to meet you. Asante.
你讓我們感到驕傲
You are doing us proud.
你們好，年輕人！
Hello, you young ones!
歐賓舒夫人?
Mrs Obinchu?
我們能談談嗎？
Can we talk'?
是的，當然
Yes, of course.
所以我們的那份呢?
So what is our cut'?
你說什麼? Excuse me?
聽著，別跟我裝傻，賤人
Look, don't act stupid with me, bitch.
為了報道馬魯格，媒體給了你錢
The press are giving you money for Maruge.
我要我那一份
I want my share.
很高興在這裡看見你們
It's good to see you here
歡迎大家
Welcome, everybody
很高興在這裡看見你們
It's good to see you here
歡迎大家...
Welcome, everybody...
幾個官員來了學校
I've got politicians turning up at school.
他們有個助手以為  媒體用錢向我買馬魯格的新聞
One of their aides thinks the press are giving me money for Maruge.
他恐嚇我
He threatened me.
你怎麼跟他說的?
What did you say to him?
我叫他離開 哦，珍妮
I told him to leave. Oh, Jane.
你一定要多加小心
You must be careful.
你在和有權勢的人頂撞
You're butting heads with powerful people.
那你想讓我怎麼辦，查爾斯?
What did you expect me to do, Charles?
你應該跟我待在奈洛比
You should be in Nairobi with me.
你在那裡我沒法保護你
I can't protect you when you're there.
好吧! OK.
我要回家了
I'm coming home.
我會取消明天的會議
I'll cancel my meetings for tomorrow.
謝謝 Thank you.
查爾斯? Charles?
對不起 I'm sorry.
我愛你 I love you.
好的 OK.
是的? Yes?
是查爾斯·歐賓舒嗎?
Charles Obinchu?
是  請稍候
Yes. Hold on a minute.
喂? Yes?
你知道你不在家的時候你妻子晚上是怎麼過的嗎？
Do you know how your wife spends her evenings when you're not there?
或許你不介意她有個男朋友，嗯？
Maybe you don't mind if she has a boyfriend, eh?
什麼男人會連自己的老婆都管不了
What kind of man can't even control his own wife
老婆跟別的男人在城裡廝混
The wife is hanging out with other men in the city
你肯定是個傻帽
You must be a fool
她就是個妓女
She's a whore
蕩婦 Slut
我們知道那些報社的人給了你一些錢
We know those newspaper people gave you some money.
我們也要一份
We want a share.
什麼錢? What money?
我沒有錢
I have no money.
老頭...別管我！
Old man...Leave me alone!
去學校並教訓一下馬魯格
Go to the school and teach Maruge a lesson.
確保不要出錯
Make sure and make no mistake.
把他從這裡永遠嚇跑
Scare him away from here for good.
不許出錯! No mistakes!
你們不許傷害孩子  聽清楚了嗎?
You don't hurt the children. Am I clear?
是的 我們今天行動
Yes. Today we are doing it.
是的! Yes!
誰是我這隊的獅子?
Who are the lions on my team?
是的! 誰是馬魯格這隊的大象?
Yes! Who are the elephants on Maruge's team?
好的，你準備好了嗎？你準備好了嗎？我們開始!
OK, are you ready? Are you set? Let's go!
好的，快點，這樣我們就能打敗...
OK, quick, so we can beat...
離窗戶遠點！離窗戶遠點！
Get away from the window! Get away from the window!
大家坐下 坐下! 法蘭西斯！離窗戶遠點！
Sit down, everybody. Sit down! Francis! Get away from the window!
走開! 蹲下!
Get away! Get down!
這是怎麼回事?
What's going on here?
你以為你能對我怎麼樣?
You think you can do anything to me?
你們能幹什麼?  你們能幹什麼?
What can you do? What can you do?
走吧，走吧! 這老牛瘋了 走吧，走吧！
Let's go, let's go. The old bull is crazy. Let's go, let's go!
別管他了!  別管他了!
Leave him! Leave him!
走吧!  夥計 我們走吧!
Let's go, man. Let's go!
走開！待在那裡，卡卯
Go away! Stay there, Kamau.
你們什麼也幹不了
You can do nothing.
事情越來越失控了，馬魯格
This is getting out of hand, Maruge.
我們很好 我們沒做錯什麼
We are alright. It's nothing wrong.
他們不會回來的
They won't come back.
我沒事 我很好
I'm OK. I'm alright.
只是幾個我剛剛惹惱的人 沒關係
Just a few people I've just annoyed. it's OK.
你還好吧? 我很好
Are you OK? I'm fine.
長脖子 Long neck,
胖肚子 tummy fat,
數字5戴著一頂帽子
number 5 wears a hat.
你可以想像那一下嗎?  卡卯
Can you imagine that? Kamau
一個人長著長脖子
A man with a long neck
而且有個大肚子，胖胖的
and a big tummy, fat,
還戴了頂帽子!
and wears a hat!
長脖子 Long neck,
胖肚子 tummy fat,
數字5戴頂帽子
number 5 wears a hat.
好的 現在我想讓你試試
Good. Now I want you to try it.
長脖子 Long neck,
胖肚子... tummy fat...
數字5戴頂帽子
number 5 wears a hat.
非常好，卡卯  非常好!
Very good, Kamau. Very good!
想再試一次嗎？是的，很好
Want to try it again? Yeah, good.
長脖子...Long neck...
胖肚子 tummy fat,
數字5戴頂帽子
number 5 wears a hat.
很好! Great!
你確定你會了嗎?
You sure you can do it?
你確定嗎？是的
Are you sure? Yes.
是的，我知道你可以！
Yes, I know you can!
而我早就知道你可以的!
And I knew you could!
是的 Yes.
給我的嗎? 是的
For me? Yes.
謝謝，祖納斯
Thanks, Jonas.
嗯？我簡直不敢相信
Hmm? I can't believe this.
他要把我調走
He's transferred me.
什麼?  調到哪裡?
What? Where to?
圖爾卡納離這裡有300英哩
Turkana is 300 miles away from here.
我們彼此應該怎麼見面？
How are we supposed to see each other?
你不能接受這次調職，這點很清楚
You're not taking that transfer, and that's clear.
噢! 我不會辭職的，查爾斯
Well, I'm not resigning, Charles.
原則上，我才不會隨了奇普托的意
I refuse to give Kipruto the satisfaction as a matter of principle.
讓原則見鬼去吧!
To hell with principle!
他們正在向教室扔血淋淋的石頭
They are throwing bloody rocks at the classroom.
他們把你調職  而我在工作中遇到了問題
They transfer you. I'm having problems at work.
難道你不知道這都是針對我們的嗎?
Can't you see what this thing is doing to us?
所以，你想讓我怎麼辦，查爾斯? 嗯？
So, what do you want me to do, Charles? Hmm?
安靜地去並閉嘴，像個好肯尼亞人一樣？
Go quietly and shut up, like a good Kenyan man?
"女人必須被看到而不是被聽到"是這樣嗎?
"Women must be seen and not heard," is that it?
你的確被人看到了，相信我
You are seen, trust me.
你被人看到了!
You are seen!
看到? Seen?
你在指責我什麼嗎？
Are you accusing me of something?
珍妮 Jane,
人們開始說閒話了
people are beginning to talk.
我日夜接到電話，告訴我一些事情
I get phone calls day and night, telling me things.
說你有外遇
That you're having an affair.
是真的嗎? Are you?
你真的有外遇嗎?
Are you having an affair?
他們還能有多下流?
How low can they go?
那你願意承受這些多久，珍?
How far are you willing to take this, Jane?
你為什麼要為了這個老頭冒一切風險？
Why are you risking everything because of this old man?
讓它去吧! Just let it go.
讓它去吧! Let it go.
查爾斯，你知道簡單的答案是什麼嗎？
You know what the simple answer is, Charles?
我就是沒法將他拒之門外
I just don't have any way to turn him away.
我會去圖爾卡納
I'll go to Turkana.
但是我不會辭職的
But I'm not resigning.
我不會向他們屈服的
I'm not giving in to them.
歡迎 謝謝
Karibu. Asante.
跟我說說你的想法
Tell me your mind.
我跟你一起去圖爾卡納
I go with you to Turkana.
我去那裡上學
I'll go to school there.
不必了，謝謝，馬魯格
No, thanks, Maruge.
我不想再起紛爭了
I don't want any more battles.
圖爾卡納很遠
Turkana is far.
你丈夫打算怎麼辦?
What about your husband?
他會留在奈洛比
He'll stay in Nairobi.
他很忙 He's very busy.
我們已經分開很久了，我們已經習慣了，是嗎？
We've been apart so much we're used to it, yeah?
因為我你受苦了
You're suffering because of me.
不 No.
這是我的決定
It's my decision.
我想我太老了學不了什麼東西
I think I'm too old to learn.
我父親有句諺語
My father had a saying.
他不是一個受過教育的人
He wasn't an educated man.
他是個漁夫
He was a fisherman.
但是他說 But he said,
"學習永遠不會結束，直到你踏進棺材"
"Learning never ends until you have got soil in your ears."
你父親是哪個部落的?
What was your father's tribe?
基西 Kisii.
湖區那邊
From the lakes.
好人 Good people.
那是很久以前的事了！
That was a long time ago!
一個英俊的男人，馬魯格！
A handsome man, Maruge!
還有你的妻子，她很漂亮
And your wife, she's very beautiful.
是的 Yes.
謝謝你的茶，馬魯格
Thank you for the tea, Maruge.
明天見，我的最後一天
I will see you tomorrow for my last day.
你知道，我媽媽從沒上過學
You know, my mother never went to school.
但是她對我說
But she said to me,
"珍妮，你一定熱愛教育"
"Jane, you must love education,"
"因為我要你比我更優秀"
"because I want you to be better than me."
現在，我是你們的母親
Now, I am your mother,
而我要告訴你們所有人
and I am telling you all
你必須熱愛教育...
you must love education...
這樣你們才能比我更優秀
so that you can be better than me
還有比我們這裡的所有老師更優秀
and all of us teachers here.
知道了嗎? 知道了
Si ndiyo? Ndiyo.
很好 Good.
我們有些人給珍妮老師買了禮物
Some of us have bought gifts for Teacher Jane.
我能看看嗎?
Can I see them?
好的，菲絲  你想讓我們開始嗎？
OK, Faith. would you like to start us off?
噢! Oh!
手鐲! 非常感謝你
A bracelet! Thank you so much.
這些是給你的，珍妮老師
These are just for you, Teacher Jane.
你看見馬魯格了嗎?
Have you seen Maruge?
沒有，我沒見過他
No, I haven't seen him.
早上好，孩子們  早上好，先生
Good morning, children. Good morning, sir.
孩子們，我是奇普托先生
Children, I am Mr Kipruto,
而我很高興宣佈新校長的任命
and I'm pleased to announce the appointment of the new head teacher,
取代珍妮老師的新校長
the new mwalimu mkuu, who will take the place of Teacher Jane.
新校長對兒童教育
The new head teacher has shown loyalty and dedication
表現出忠誠和奉獻精神
to the education of children
而我們覺得這次提拔她是實至名歸的
and we feel is greatly deserving of this promotion.
我希望你們全力支持格蕾絲·穆桑巴夫人
I expect you to show your full support for Mrs Grace Muthumba.
今天下午她就會來跟我們見面
She'll be joining us this afternoon.
所以在此期間，我會暫代她的職位
So in the meantime, I'll be standing in her place.
我以前也是個老師 所以我們會玩得很開心，對嗎？
I used to be a teacher. So we'll have fun, right?
是的 Yes.
好了，孩子們  然後你們還要去上課 然後你們還要去上課
Alright, children. And then you've got class. And then you've got class.
不要跑! 不要跑，不要跑，不要跑，不要跑
No running! No running, no running, no running, no running.
走吧!  走吧!  走吧!
Let's go, let's go, let's go.
我需要去城裡
I need to go to the city.
你要去城裡? 來吧!
You're going to the city? Let's go.
那是我的車費 什麼?
That's my fare. What?
我該怎麼處理這隻山羊，馬魯格?
What am I going to do with a goat, Maruge?
你可以飼養更多的山羊
You can breed more goats.
哦，拜託，馬魯格 我必須儘快趕到城裡
Oh, come on, Maruge. I've got to get to the city quickly.
這不公平  馬魯格，下次你要帶現金
That's not fair. Maruge, next time you need to get hard cash.
免費教育把你搞砸了，馬魯格
Free education is messing you up, Maruge.
她到了! She's here!
你好! 這麼多的面孔
Hello! So many faces.
來吧! Come on.
你來上鎖
You get the padlock.
快點，快點，快點
Faster, faster, faster.
退回去!
Move back!
退回去，退回去，退回去
Go back. Go back, go back.
好了，扔，扔!
OK, throw. Throw!
我們要珍妮老師! 我們要珍妮老師!
We want Teacher Jane! We want Teacher Jane!
珍妮老師!
Teacher Jane!
馬魯格，你那該死的山羊在這裡的每個人身上撒尿！
Maruge, your damn goat is peeing on everyone here!
嘿，那是什麼？你回學校真是個白癡
Hey, what's that? You're an idiot for going back to school.
這個名人宣傳現在做得太過火了!
This celebrity culture has gone too far now!
你，現在住手
You, stop that, now.
不!  你看看他們! 我不能容忍這種不守紀律的行為！
No! Look at them! I can't handle such indiscipline!
他們只是...小孩子們！ 他們只是小...
They're just...little children! They're just little...
嘿，我們可以處理他們！
Hey, we can take care of them!
不!  格蕾絲，別這樣!
No! Grace, please!
他們只是小孩子!
They're just little kids!
我們要珍妮老師! 我們要珍妮老師!
We want Teacher Jane! We want Teacher Jane!
抱歉! Sorry!
格蕾絲! Grace!
哇! 歡迎!  每個人都在這裡
Wo, karibu! This is where everybody is.
但別擔心，我們有更好的地方，好嗎？
But don't worry, we have a better place, alright?
那沒有示威 很多人都在做他們的事，馬魯格
There's no demonstration. So many people are doing their business, Maruge.
小心，小心！
Watch out, watch out!
當你在這裡迷路時，就亮出身份證就行了
When you get lost here, just raise your ID.
哇-哇！奈洛比，我們來了
Wah-wah! Nairobi, here we come.
這就是奈洛比!
This is Nairobi!
讓教育運動的老傢伙
Got the old guy from the education campaign
和我一起在接待處
here with me in reception.
他想見主席
He wants to see the chairman.
好的，謝謝
OK, thanks.
不好意思  主席在忙
Excuse me. The chairman is busy.
你想見副主席嗎?
would you like to see the deputy chairman?
不要，哦...好吧!
No. Oh...alright.
那恐怕你得等一等
Then I'm afraid you'll have to wait.
我不想等
I don't want to wait.
你必須等
You're gonna have to.
嘿，傑姬，我需要讓主席簽署這份文件
Hey, Jacquie, I need the chairman to sign this.
不，抱歉，他正在開會，我不能打擾他
No, sorry, he's in a meeting and I cannot disturb him.
但是我現在就要
But I need it right now.
好的，把這個交給我，然後我看看我能做什麼
OK, do this leave it with me, then I'll see what I can do.
好的，但要儘快 當然
OK, but make it ASAP. Sure.
嘿，先生！等等! 請稍候！
Hey, sir! Wait! Please wait!
那麼，我們該何去何從?
So, where do we go from here?
主席先生，我仍然堅持我們應該去基利菲
Mr Chairman, I still insist that we should go to Kilifi.
我們有資金!
We have the money!
等等  先生!
Wait, sir!
老人，你不能進去...
Old man, you can't go in...
對不起，主席先生
I am so sorry, Mr Chairman.
我這就去叫保安
I'm gonna go and call security.
這是怎麼回事?
What is this?
先生，這位是馬魯格老人
Sir, this is Mzee Maruge.
馬魯格先生 我們能為您做些什麼？
Mr Maruge. What can we do for you?
我來這裡為了要回一個老師
I'm here for a teacher.
先生，我應該...不，沒關係 謝謝你
Sir, shall I...No, that's alright. Thank you.
我們注意到你了，先生
You have our attention, sir.
我跟我們的開國元勳一起待過拘留營
I was in the detention camps with our founding fathers.
這些人為你們這一代犧牲了一切
These men sacrificed everything for your generation.
沒有他們，你們就不會待在這裡
Without them, you'd not be here.
之前，那裡只掛著英國女王像
Before, it was only the Queen's face there.
英國人這樣對我
The British did this to me.
他們壓碎了我的頭骨
They cracked my skull.
他們砍斷了我的腳趾
They chopped off my toes.
主席先生...
Mr Chairman...
馬魯格先生，那已經夠了
Mr Maruge, that's enough.
我們必須向我們的過去學習
We have to learn from our past.
我們不能忘記
We must not forget.
但是我們要做得更好
But we must be better.
我們需要好的教師
We need good teachers.
我們給孩子播下什麼就會收穫什麼
We reap what we sow with our children.
把她調回來
Bring her back.
謝謝 Thank you.
歡迎回來
Welcome back.
那是誰? 是珍妮老師!
Who is it? It's Teacher Jane!
老師!  珍妮老師回來了  我們能去看她嗎?
Teacher! Teacher Jane is here. Can we go to her?
歡迎回來!
Welcome back!
噢! 我們都很想你
Oh, we missed you so much.
歡迎! Welcome!
歡迎回來!
Welcome back!
我聽說你們一直都有寫作業  你們一直都有寫嗎?
I hear you have been writing. Is it true you have been writing?
好了  回去上課!  好的，來
Alright, back to class! OK, come.
我們快回去上課
Let's go back to class.
我希望你能永遠回來
I hope you're back for good.
好的，所以我們來決定用哪本書...
OK, so let's decide which books are going...
是的，馬魯格?
Yes, Maruge?
我們很忙，馬魯格 不，沒關係
We're busy, Maruge. No, it's OK.
這封信，太難讀了  你現在必須給我讀一下
The letter, is too hard. You must read it for me now.
求求你 Please.
來吧!  馬魯格
Come, Maruge.
你給馬魯格讀
You read it for Maruge.
坐下，馬魯格
Sit down, Maruge.
"尊敬的4339號囚犯"
"Dear honoured prisoner number 4339,"
"僅代表肯尼亞共和國"
"on behalf of the Republic of Kenya"
"我想通知您，您已被判定有資格獲得賠償”
"I would like to inform you that you have been judged eligible for compensation"
"因為你在殖民統治下被監禁期間所遭受的虐待”
"for the ill-treatment you endured while imprisoned under colonial rule"
"1951年至1953年在霍拉營地”
"in Hola camp from 1951 to 1953,"
"1953年至1955年的蘭家塔營地..."
"Langata camp from 1953 to 1955..."
"1955年至1957年的曼亞尼營地"
Manyani camp from 1955 to 1957,
"1957至1959年  囚禁於因巴喀西營地"
Embakasi camp from 1957 to 1959."
"根據紀錄  4339號囚犯"
it is recorded hereby that prisoner number 4339
"由於堅持拒絕放棄誓言"
"suffered cruel and inhuman treatment in captivity"
"在拘禁期間受到了殘忍和不人道的虐待"
"because of his sustained refusal to renounce the oath of allegiance."
"感謝你為了解放我們國家所作的英勇犧牲"
"with gratitude for your heroic sacrifice in liberating our country,"
"肯尼亞共和國總統閣下"
"His Excellency the president of the Republic of Kenya"
我們能有今天都是因為你  馬魯格
We can have today It's all because of you, maruge
我們走吧，馬魯格？
Shall we go, Maruge?
這並不意味著我的學習結束，你知道嗎？
This is not the end, you know?
我想繼續學習
I want to continue learning.
我想當獸醫
I want to become a vet.
獸醫，馬魯格？
A vet, Maruge?
但你知道你大約100歲了嗎？
But you know you'll be about 100 years old?
我會學到踏進棺材的那天
I'll learn until I have soil in my ears.
是的，馬魯格 你會的 你會的
Yes, Maruge. You will. You will.
奇曼尼·囊·馬魯格作為上小學的最年長者
獲得了吉尼斯紀錄
他受邀到位於紐約的聯合國
向各國政要作題為教育的力量的演講
馬魯格鼓勵了新一代首次走進校園
奇曼尼·囊·馬魯格(1920——2009)
同胞們，同胞們
My People, my people,
老師，我的老師，哇!
teacher, my teacher, wow!
現在消息已經正式傳開了
Now, word has spread, officially,
奇曼尼·囊·馬魯格他自己
that Kimani Ng'ang'a Maruge has actually made it all the way
獨自一路來到了美利堅合眾國
to the United States of America all by himself,
向聯合國演說，跟各國政要講話
speaking to the UN, to talk to the politicians.
這真讓人難以置信!
This is unbelievable!
我...我甚至不敢...
L...l cannot even...
馬魯格在美國，向聯合國作演講!
Maruge in the United States, speaking to the UN!
你能...你能相信嗎？
Can you...Can you believe that?
你知道，我現在...我現在開始相信
You know, I'm now...I'm now beginning to believe
有一天，一個肯尼亞人 一個肯尼亞人可以入主白宮
that one day, a Kenyan a Kenyan! will go to the White House.
但現在...據我所說
But for now...according to me,
奇曼尼·馬魯格是全世界的校長!
Kimani Maruge is the headmaster of the world!
是的，我們能!
Yes, we can!